A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor John Buchanan Floyd, 1849-1851
Library of Virginia
- Executive Papers of Governor John Buchanan Floyd, 1849-1851., Extent: 11 boxes. (Box 1-11)
  Additional significant correspondence includes the following: John M. Seely re. his claim against the Commonwealth for painting & glazing the Capitol (1849 Jan. 15); John D. Scott, Commandant of the Gosport Navy Yard, re. the transfer of a brass gun formerly belonging to the Centipede (1849 Mar. 10); William H. Richardson re. the removal of the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth to the former court room of the Court of Appeals (1849 Mar. 24); H. Rhodes, President of the Belvidere Manufacturing Company, asks for permission to conduct waste water from Capitol Square to the Franklin Paper Mill (1849 Apr. 24); E. Brown resigning as first lieutenant of the Public Guard (1849 Aug. 7); Robertson Topp & others, Memphis, re. a convention to be held in Memphis for the purpose of constructing a central railway from the Mississippi River to the Pacific Ocean (1849 Sept. 15); B.B. Minor asking for the privilege of erecting a one-story tenement for the accommodation of a reading room for his newly established law building on Franklin Street near the Courthouse (includes map) (1849 Apr. 30); Gessner Harrison, Chairman of the faculty of the University of Virginia, re. the transfer of state documents intended for the University Library (1850 Jan. 21); Indiana Colonization Society re. the removal of free persons of color to Africa (1850 Mar. 22); James A. Seddon, House of Representatives, re. the removal of the remains of John C. Calhoun to South Carolina (1850 Apr. 16), C.C. Wright, New York, re. a medal for General Scott (1850 Apr. 29); Robert Mills, Washington, re. his plans for the extension of the Capitol at Richmond (1850 May 20); William St. Clair Clarke, Washington, encl. a memorial of Joseph Bryan to Congress proposing a line of steamships between the U.S. & Africa to suppress the slave trade & convey free people of color to Africa (1850 May 10); Archibald Graham, Lexington, re. a request for a block of marble (1850 June 1); letters of application for director of the Eastern Lunatic Asylum (1850 June); John Notman, Philadelphia, encl. a report on the public grounds of the Capitol in Richmond (1850 July 22); Lewis E. Harvie re. the opening of a street on the line of the Armory property (1850 July 5); Robert Mills, Washington, re. specimens of granite for use in Crawford's statue of Washington on Capitol Square (1850 July 22); William J. McAlpin & Robert Mills re. the proper salary for O.H. Rand, Superintendent of the Virginia Washington Monument (1850 Aug. 27); Samuel Clarke, Sr., proposing to furnish trees for Capitol Square (1850 Sept. 17); Jacob Barby re. furnishing a block of marble for the National Washington Monument (1850 May 27 & Oct. 23); D.H. Mahan, Chairman of the Board of Engineers, U.S. Military Academy, re. a claim against the Baltimore & Ohio Railroad Company (1850 Oct. 2); A.A. Chapman, Staunton, recommending John F.J. White as director of the Deaf & Dumb Institute (1850 Nov. 8); Samuel G. Daniel, Fredericksburg, re. the establishment of the Fredericksburg Female Institute (1850 Oct. 25); D.H. Mahan, U.S. Military Academy, encl. various papers from Meriwether Lewis Clark, Secretary of the Board of Engineers of the U.S. Military Academy, & others re. the dispute between the City of Wheeling and the Baltimore & Ohio Railroad Company (1850 Nov. 18); S.G.M. Merrillat re. the appointment of a Board of Visitors for the Institution for the Deaf, Dumb, & the Blind at Staunton (1850 Dec. 18); Franklin Peale, Mint of the United States, Chief Coiners Office, Philadelphia, re. a medal to commemorate the gallant services of General Scott (1850 Dec. 27); Francis H. Smith, Superintendent of the Virginia Military Academy, re. an insurrectionary letter planning an attack on the academy & requesting fixed ammunition (1851 Jan. 2); Richard Parker acknowledging receipt of his commission as judge of the 13th Judicial Circuit (1851 Jan. 29); James E. Heath, Commissioner of Pensions, encl. a printed copy of the act granting bounty land to certain officers & soldiers who have been engaged in the military service of the United States (1851 Feb. 4); George P. Putnam, N.Y., re. Mr. Turner's refusal to deliver plates of the map of Virginia (1851 Feb. 28); Samuel Jackson, Baltimore, re. the sword voted by the Legislature to Capt. Otway Byrd (1851 Mar. 10); James E. Heath, Commissioner of Pensions, re. the Bounty Land Act of Sept. 28, 1850 (1851 Mar. 20); E.S. Gay, Superintendent of the Washington Monument, encl. a letter from Robert Mills, Architect, re. the bill of G.T. Rodgers for stone cutter's work on the monument (1851 Apr. 18); J.Y. Mason, President of the Convention, encl. a certified copy of the Bill of Rights, Constitution, & Schedule (1851 Aug. 1); Fredrich von Gerolt, Prussian Legation at Washington, requesting information in regard to the financial organization & the revenue system of the state of Virginia (1851 Oct. 30); N.W. Pollard re. the cost of deporting the whole free colored population of Virginia (1851 Oct. 2); George P. Scarburgh resigning as judge of the General Court (1851 Nov. 26); P.T. Howard, Assistant Secretary of the Commonwealth, re. the deed of cession for the lot on Hog Island in Northampton County to the United States for a lighthouse to be erected on the south end of the island (1851 Oct. 17); C.A. Alexander, Alexandria, encl. a proposal & plans for building a gun house in Alexandria (1851 Nov. 24); E.S. Gay re. the discharge of slaves employed on the Washington Monument (1851 Dec. 10); and James S. French re. his claim to a public highway through United State land at Old Point Comfort (1851 Dec. 12).
  Other noteworthy items include the following: a proclamation of Governor Floyd for an election to supply the vacancy in the State Senate occasioned by the resignation of Thomas H. Averett (1849 Mar. 29); a proclamation of Governor Floyd for an election to supply the vacancy in the House of Delegates occasioned by the resignation of Lewis Beard (1849 Apr. 17); a report of the commissioners to examine the construction of an additional furnace by the Armory Iron Company close to the Armory (1849 May 19); resolutions of New Hampshire re. slavery (1849 July 7); proclamations of Governor Floyd & Lt. Governors John M. Patton & Raleigh T. Daniel offering rewards for the arrest of escaped convicts (1849 Aug. 9, Sept. 11, Dec. 26 & 28, 1850 Jan. 28 & 31, Feb. 1, 14 & 16, June 21, July 19, Oct. 1 & 31, Dec. 23 & 28, 1851 Jan. 3, Mar. 3 & 29, May 9 & 31, July 8, Sept. 12, Oct. 11, 20, & 24, Nov. 28); a proclamation of Lt. Governor John M. Patton for an election to supply the vacancy in the House of Representatives occasioned by the death of Alexander Newman (1849 Sept. 12); a proclamation of Lt. Governor John M. Patton for an election to supply the vacancy in the State Senate occasioned by the resignation of Edward P. Scott (1849 Sept. 28); recommendations of Robert G. Scott as lieutenant of the Public Guard (1849 Oct. 30); recommendations for Elliott M. Braxton as lieutenant of the Public Guard (1849 Oct. 16); a proclamation of Governor Floyd appointing Henry Van Buren weighmaster of livestock at Richmond (1850 Dec. 19); petition of James Barron re. the Revolutionary service of his father Commodore James Barron of the Virginia Navy (1850 Mar. 25); proceedings of the City Council appointing committees to make arrangements for the reception of John C. Calhoun's remains (1850 Apr. 18); a proclamation of Governor Floyd for a general election for delegates to a convention (1850 June 4); articles of agreement between Thomas Crawford & Governor Floyd to model & complete in bronze the Virginia Washington Monument on Capitol Square (1850 June 27); proceedings of a meeting of the President & Director of the James River & Kanawha Canal Company re. the remittance of tolls for the transportation of stone used in the construction of the Washington Monument from the quarry to the basin (1850 Oct. 12); a proclamation of Governor Floyd for an election to supply the vacancy in the House of Delegates occasioned by the death of John Akers of Patrick County (1850 Oct. 25); a proclamation of Governor Floyd for an election to supply the vacancy in the House of Delegates occasioned by the resignation of N.C. Claiborne of Franklin County (1850 Nov. 2); Westham Magazine surveys from 1814 (1851 Mar. 25); joint resolutions of the state of Illinois re. slavery & the system of adjustment or compromise for the admission of California, the establishment of territorial governments for Utah & New Mexico, etc. (1851 Jan. 6); proclamation of Lt. Gov. John F. Wiley re. the adjournment of the convention assembled to consider, discuss, & propose a new constitution (includes copy of bill of rights, constitution, & schedule) (1851 Aug. 2); a proclamation of Governor Floyd to the sheriffs, constables, & other peace officers of the state for the arrest of Henry R. Page to be delivered to William H. Jarman to be taken back to Alabama (1851 Nov. 6); a proclamation of Governor Floyd declaring that a large majority of votes were cast in favor of ratifying the Constitution as amended (1851 Nov. 17); articles of agreement between Governor Floyd & John A. Temple & Company to rent the granite quarries upon the state property known as the Old Magazine tract for two years on the condition that they furnish all stone necessary for the completion of the Washington Monument on Capitol Square (1851 Dec. 22); and recommendations for George W. Dixon as lieutenant of the Public Guard (undated).
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1849
    - January
      - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - February
      - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 16-28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - March
      - 1-19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 21-30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - April
      - 2-19 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 20-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - May
      - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - June
      - 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 16-29 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - July
      - 2-16 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 17-30 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - August
      - 4-15 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - September
      - 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - October
      - 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 16-31 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - November
      - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 17-30 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - December
      - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Undated. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1850
    - January
      - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - 16-23 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - 24-31 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - February
      - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - 16-28 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - March
      - 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 16-20 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - 21-30 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - April
      - 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - 16-30 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - May
      - 1-10 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - 11-20 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 21-31 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - June
      - 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - 17-25 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - 26-30 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - July
      - 1-10 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - 11-20 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - 21-31 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - August
      - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - 16-29 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - 30-31 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - September
      - 1-14 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - October
      - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - 16-31 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - November
      - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - 16-30 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - December
      - 1-17 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - 18-31 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Undated. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1851
    - January
      - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - 16-26 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - 27-31 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - February
      - 3-15 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - 17-27 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - March
      - 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - 17-31 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - April
      - 2-15 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - 16-29 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - May
      - 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - 16-31 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - June
      - 1-14 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - 16-30 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - July
      - 1-15 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - 16-31 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - August
      - 1-9 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - 11-30 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - September
      - 1-15 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - 16-30 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - October
      - 1-10 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - 11-22 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - 23-31 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - November
      - 1-10 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - 11-20 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - 21-30 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - December
      - 1-15 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - 16-30 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Oversized (Clamshell Box)
  - 1849
    - Mar. 9 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Dec. 1 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1850
    - Feb. 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - May 16 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - [N.D.] (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 1851
    - Feb. 4 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - May 20 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - June 1 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - June 9 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Oct. 15 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Oct. 18 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Oct. 28 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Nov. 24 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Undated. (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Oversized (Newspaper Box)
  - 1849
    - Apr. 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Apr. 16 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 1850
    - Apr. 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - May 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - June 11 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Nov. 12 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 1851
    - Mar. 31 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Apr. 5 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Apr. 12 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Apr. 18 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Apr. 23 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - May 5 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - June 2 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - June 9 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - June 10 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - June 30 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - July 22 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Aug. 16 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Aug. 21 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Aug. 27 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Oct. 1 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Oct. 11 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Oct. 18 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Nov. 3 (Box 11, Folder 24)